RG 081, Department of Connecticut United Spanish War Veterans
Connecticut State Library
Department of Connecticut United Spanish War Veterans records
1898-1973
Connecticut State Library
United Spanish War Veterans. Dept. of Connecticut
25 cubic feet
The United Spanish War Veterans was organized in 1904 by the amalgamation of a number of veterans organizations, including the National Army and Navy Spanish War Veterans, the National Association Spanish-American War Veterans, the Service Men of the Spanish War.
RG081
1973-003
Historical Note
The United Spanish War Veterans was organized in 1904 by the amalgamation of a number of veterans organizations, including the National Army and Navy Spanish War Veterans, the National Association Spanish-American War Veterans, the Service Men of the Spanish War, etc. According to the Constitution and Rules and Regulations United Spanish War Veterans, 1951, Art. 3, it was composed of men and women who "served at any time during the war between the United States of America and the Kingdom of Spain, or at any time during the war for the suppression of the insurrection in the Philippine Islands, including the China Relief Expedition [from April 21, 1898]…to July 4, 1902…"
Among its objects were to unite in fraternal bonds those who served during the War with Spain or the campaigns growing out of that war; to honor the dead; to assist former comrades and their families; to perpetuate the memories of the war and to collect and preserve the records of service of the individual members of the Order; to inculcate the principles of universal liberty, equal rights and justice to all mankind, etc.
The Department of Connecticut was divided into 31 local camps which reported to the Department and met annually in an encampment.
Scope and Content
The records include office files; rosters and papers relating to the individual camps; papers relating to various encampments and social events; photos and memorabilia, including a diary written by Catharine Pilgard, a nurse who served during the Spanish-American War; financial records; secretary's records; and published materials.
Arrangement
Series 1. Office Files, 1946-1971.
Series 2. Rosters, correspondence with camps, and related papers, 1947-1971.
Series 3. Encampments and Social Events, 1927-1971
Series 4. Catharine D. Pilgard Materials, 1898, 1939-1941.
Series 5. Unsorted correspondence and papers, 1938-1972.
Series 6. Photographs and memorabilia.
Series 7. Financial Records, 1920-1972.
Series 8. Secretary's Records, 1932-1971.
Series 9. Per Capita Tax Returns, 1941-1971
Series 10. Reports, 1918-1940.
Series 11. Published Material, 1904-1973.
Series 12. Scrapbook, 1898.
Series 13. Card File of United Spanish War Veterans.
Series 14. Charter, 1932.
Related Material
, Connecticut State Library.
Separated Material
The following items were transferred to the Museum of Connecticut History.
1. 1 large cannon bullet.
2. 1 kit for soldier with bullets and pipe.
3. 1 small box with two metal stamps.
4. 1 Charles P. Dunlay notary stamp.
5. 1 1/2 boxes of plaques.
6. 1 medal in envelope.
7. 1 bunch of delegate ribbons.
8. 1 envelope containing Charles B. Linke medals.
9. 1 flag.
10. 1 gavel.
11. 2 boxes containing various medals.
12. 1 die for medals.
13. 1 old native Philippine comb.
14. 1 box containing medals and 1 die and buttons.
15. 2 silver cups.
16. 1 USWV banner.
17. 2 frames containing medals, buttons, etc.
Index Terms
Organizations:
United Spanish War Veterans. Dept. of Connecticut
Persons:
Pilgard, Catharine D.
Subjects:
United Spanish War Veterans. Dept. of Connecticut -- Records and correspondence; Spanish-American War, 1898 -- Connecticut -- Societies, etc.
Document Types:
Account books; Cashbooks; Charters; Check stubs; Correspondence; Financial records; Ledgers (account books); Minutes; Pamphlets; Photographs; Reports; Rosters; Scrapbooks
Restrictions on Access
See the policy.
Provenance
In February 1973, the records came to the State Library under Section 27-131a of the General Statutes of Connecticut: "…If, at any time, said department is dissolved or ceases to exist or becomes inactive, said records shall become the property of the state of Connecticut and shall be transferred to the department of war records of the state library…"
Container List
- Series 1. Office Files, 1946-1971
  - Council of Administration minutes, 1946-1964 (Box 1)
  - General orders, 1959-1970 (Box 1)
  - Installation reports, 1964-1969 (Box 1)
  - Legislation, national and state, correspondence, 1947-1962 (Box 1)
  - Mailings, listings, etc., 1948-1970 (Box 1)
  - Murphy, Newton, Comrade correspondence, 1968-1970 (Box 1)
  - National aides de Camp correspondence, 1947-1969 (Box 1)
  - National semi-annual tax reports, 1946-1971 (Box 1)
  - National Headquarters U.S.W.V. (Box 1)
  - Newspaper clippings, circa 1943-1960 (Box 2)
  - Pending folio, correspondence, 1961-1967 (Box 2)
  - Rocky Hill Home Day & Christmas Cheer reports, correspondence, etc., 1949-1968 (Box 2)
  - Rosters of department officers, 1930-1970 (Box 2)
  - VA Voluntary Service Advisory Committee minutes, 1968-1970 (Box 2)
  - Veterans benefits, new program, 1967 (Box 2)
  - Veterans miscellaneous inquiries, 1947-1969 (Box 2)
  - Veterans Administration Regional Office (Box 2)
  - Widows benefits correspondence, 1947-1969 (Box 2)
- Series 2. Rosters, correspondence with camps, and related papers, 1947-1971
  Arranged numerically by camp.
  - Allan Osborn Camp No. 1, New Haven (Box 3)
  - Charles B. Bowen Camp No. 2, Meriden (Box 3)
  - Lieut. N. W. Bishop Camp No. 3, Bridgeport (Box 3)
  - Charles L. Burdett Camp No. 4, Hartford (Box 3)
  - A. G. Hammond Camp No. 5, New Britain (Box 3)
  - Major R. S. Griswold Camp No. 6, Norwich (Box 3)
  - George M. Cole Camp No. 7, New London (Box 3)
  - Col. A. C. Tyler Camp No. 8, Willimantic (Box 3)
  - William McKinley Camp No. 9, Norwalk (Box 3)
  - Sidney Beach Camp No. 10, Bridgeport (Box 3)
  - Emerson H. Liscum Camp No. 12, Waterbury (Box 3)
  - Ward Cheney Camp No. 13, Manchester (Box 3)
  - James W. Milne Camp No. 14, Rockville (Box 3)
  - Frederick A. Hill Camp No. 15, Stamford (Box 3)
  - Charles P. Kirkland Camp No. 18, Winsted (Box 3)
  - W. S. Steele Camp No. 19, Torrington (Box 3)
  - William H. Hamilton Camp No. 20, Danielson (Box 3)
    See Series 14 for charter.
  - George A. Hadsell Camp No. 21, Bristol (Box 3)
  - Milford Camp No. 22, Milford (Box 3)
  - Frederick Fuller Camp No. 24, Guilford (Box 3)
  - Gen. Nelson A. Miles camp No. 25, Middletown (Box 3)
  - Ernest Weichert Camp No. 26, Danbury (Box 3)
  - Gen. Joe Wheeler Camp No. 28, Ansonia (Box 3)
  - A. Wilder Merriam Camp No. 29, Putnam (Box 3)
  - William G. Bee Camp No. 31, East Hartford (Box 3)
  - Gen. Edward Schulze Camp No. 31, West Hartford (Box 3)
- Series 3. Encampments and Social Events, 1927-1971
  - Convention audits, 1955-1968 (Box 3)
    Includes correspondence, paid bills, etc.
  - Department encampments, dinners, programs, 1943-1970 (Box 3-4)
    Includes correspondence, financial and other reports, resolutions, guest lists, plus a list of comrades entitled to vote at the 30th encampment, 1933.
  - Department memorials, 1947-1955 (Box 4)
    Correspondence, questionnaires, and minutes of the Spanish War Memorial Committee.
  - Charles P. Dunlay correspondence, 1937-1939 (Box 4)
  - National encampments, 1951-1971 (Box 4)
    Correspondence, forms, lists, notes, etc.
  - Charles W. Newton correspondence, 1927-1930 (Box 4)
  - United Spanish War Veterans Auxiliary, 1949-1971 (Box 4)
    Department Presidents' letters, general orders, reports, correspondence.
- Series 4. Catharine D. Pilgard Materials, 1898-1900, 1939-1941
  Pilgard was a nurse on the transport Lampasas during the Spanish American war.
  - Diary, 1898 July 4 - August 8; 1 volume (Box 4)
  - Photographs taken on Lampasas + letter, 1898, 1900; 21 small snapshots (Box 4)
  - Letters re claim for pension and bill for her relief, 1939-1941 (Box 4)
- Series 5. Unsorted correspondence and papers, 1938-1972
  - Records, 1938-1972 (Box 5)
    Includes one folder of unsorted newspaper clippings.
    Arranged chronologically by year.
- Series 6. Photographs and memorabilia
  - Award for service to the community to William B. Heald, 1964 October (Box 5)
    Plus envelope of photographs.
  - Cuba, 1928; 2 photographs (Box 5)
  - Pass issued to Private Max J. Schiessl, 1898 June 27 (Box 5)
    Issued in Fort Knox, Maine.
  - Photograph of President McKinley's coffin (Box 5)
  - State Arsenal and Armory Dedication at Hartford, Conn. program, 1909 November 12 (Box 5)
  - Miscellaneous photographs (Box 23 and oversize map case)
- Series 7. Financial Records, 1920-1972
  - Account book, 1920-1921; 1 volume (Box 6)
    Contains receipts and disbursements of United Spanish War Veterans, Dept. of Connecticut. Also accounts of World War Veterans Relief Fund.
  - "Financial Administration. State of Connecticut. Staff Interim Report No. 1. The Comptroller's Department with Special Reference to Accounting and Auditing.", 1927 May 26; carbon copy (Box 6)
  - Cash books, 1934-1957; 2 volumes (Box 6)
    Cash book for 1957-1971 was returned to the organization several years ago.
  - Ledgers, 1934-1970; 3 volumes (Box 6)
    Contain debits, credits, and other accounts of various camps.
  - Record book of convention, encampment, and banquet accounts, 1949-1956; 1 volume (Box 6)
  - Financial report, 1955 June 4 (Box 6)
  - Donations, 1956-1957; 1 volume (Box 6)
  - Audit reports, appropriations and expenditures, budget summaries, inventories of property, and other papers relating to funds or grants received from the State of Connecticut, circa 1964-1972 (Box 7)
  - Hartford National Bank and Trust Co., 1939-1972 (Box 7)
    - Check stubs, 1939-1966 (Box 7)
      1968-1971 returned to organization.
      - 1939 November 23 - 1942 November 11, 1 volume (Box 7)
      - 1955 June 24 - 1957 July 24, 1 volume (Box 7)
      - 1957 March 6 - 1961 July 19, 1 volume (Box 7)
      - 1963 December 16 - 1966 February 14, 1 volume (Box 7)
      - Blank checkbook (Box 7)
    - Bank statements and cancelled checks (Box 7)
      - 1942 June - 1943 May (Box 7)
      - 1965 June - 1966 April (Box 7)
      - 1968 June - 1972 August (Box 7)
  - Phoenix State Bank and Trust Company, 1951-1955 (Box 7)
    - Check stubs (Box 7)
      - 1951 April 13 - 1953 June 1, 1 volume (Box 7)
      - 1953 June 15 - 1955 June 15, 1 volume (Box 7)
  - Connecticut Bank and Trust Company, 1963-1972 (Box 7)
    - Bank statements and cancelled checks, 1954 June - 1955 June, 1977 July 29 - 1980 May 9 (Box 7)
    - Check stubs (Box 7)
      - 1963 July 30 - 1966 February 14 (Box 7)
      - 1966 February 14 - 1968 August 15 (Box 7)
      - Blank checkbook (Box 7)
    - Envelope of "Unaudited ck book and cancelled cks for Current Audit 1970-71 & 1971-1972" (Box 7)
      - Check stubs, 1968 September 3 - 1971 March 30 (Box 7)
      - Bank statements and cancelled checks (Box 7)
        - 1965 July - 1966 October (Box 7)
        - 1968 November - 1971 July (Box 7)
        - 1972 August, November (Box 7)
      - Phoenix State Bank and Trust Company bank book (Box 7)
- Series 8. Secretary's Records, 1932-1971
  - Minutes of meetings of the Major L. B. Almy Auxiliary #15, U.S.W.V., 1934-1964 (Box 8)
    - 1934-1951, 1 volume (Box 8)
    - 1951-1964, 1 volume (Box 8)
  - Minutes or reports of proceedings of annual encampments, 1932-1935, 1939, 1956-1958, 1960-1970 (Box 8)
    Starts with 29th, ends with 67th.
  - Mortuary record, 1 volume (Box 8)
    Men buried in cemetery.
  - Desk telephone and address listing, 1 volume (Box 8)
  - Stenographer's notebook, 3 memo books, 2 receipt books, 1 "Taps Record," "Roster of...Officers," and telephone directory, circa 1956-1971; 1 folder (Box 8)
- Series 9. Per Capita Tax Returns, 1941-1971
  - 1941 June - 1952 December (Box 9)
  - 1954 January - 1971 June (Box 9)
- Series 10. Reports, 1918-1940
  - Inspection reports, 1918-1939 (Box 9)
    By camp to Connecticut Dept.
  - Indorsement reports, 1920-1940 (Box 9)
    By camp.
  - Quartermaster reports, 1917-1926 (Box 9)
- Series 11. Published Material, 1904-1973
  - By-Laws. Dept. of Connecticut., 1922, 1934; 2 pamphlets (Box 10)
  - Strickland, Daniel W. Connecticut Fights: The Story of the 102nd Regiment Quinnipiack Press, 1930, 1 volume (Box 10)
  - Connecticut Laws Affecting Veterans and their Dependents, 1947, 1953, 1958, 1960, 1968; 5 pamphlets (Box 10)
  - Connecticut Men in the Army, Navy and Marine Corps of the United States in the Spanish-American War, Philippine Insurrection and China Relief Expedition. From April 21, 1898 to July 4, 1904. Case, Lockwood & Brainard Company, 1919 (Box 10)
  - The Connecticut State Soldiers' Sailors' and Marines' Fund, 1 pamphlet (Box 10)
  - Constitution and Rules and Regulations of the United Spanish War Veterans, 1920, 1930, 1936, 1941, 1951; 5 volumes (Box 10)
  - Etiquette of the Stars and Stripes, 1 pamphlet (Box 10)
  - Federal Benefits for veterans and Dependents. VA Fact Sheet, 1965 January (Box 10)
  - The Flag of Destiny, 1 pamphlet (Box 10)
  - General Orders, 1939-1940; 41 items (Box 10)
  - Holy Bible (Box 10)
  - Proceedings of Annual Encampments of the Dept. of Connecticut United Spanish War Veterans: 33rd - 52nd, 1936-1955; 20 pamphlets (Box 10)
  - Proceedings of the 53d National Encampment United Spanish War Veterans, Grand Rapids, Mich., 1951 August 26-30; 1 volume (Box 10)
  - Proceedings of the 53d National Encampment United Spanish War Veterans, Grand Rapids, Mich., 1964 August 30 - September 3; 1 volume (Box 10)
  - Programs of annual encampments and conventions, 1915-1965; 45 pamphlets (Box 11)
  - Connecticut's 1949 Independence Day Program, Hall of Flags, State Capitol, 1949 July 4; 1 pamphlet (Box 11)
  - Register of the Connecticut Commandery of the Naval and Military Order of the Spanish-American War, Hartford, Conn., 1904; 1 volume (Box 11)
  - Maris, Jesse C. "Remembering", 1 pamphlet (Box 11)
  - Reports and Proceedings of Conventions of National Auxiliary, United Spanish War Veterans (Box 11)
    - 1904-1906, 1913 (Box 11)
    - 1910-1924 (Box 11)
    - 1925-1929 (Box 11)
  - Ritual Books, 1907-1952; 12 volumes (Box 11)
    Not all years included.
  - Rosters, 1922-1969; 38 pamphlets (Box 11)
  - "Target" Vol. XXIII, No. 3, February 1973. Veterans Home and Hospital, Rocky Hill (Box 11)
  - Wright's Official History of the Spanish-American War, 1900; 1 large oversize volume (Box Item 12)
- Series 12. Scrapbook, 1898
  - Scrapbook of clippings from newspapers and magazines, 1898; 1 large oversize volume (Box Item 13)
- Series 13. Card File of United Spanish War Veterans
  Card files B and C contain cards with record of service of Connecticut men who served in the war.
  - Card File A
    - Living as of November 1972 (Box 14)
    - Deceased
      - A - G (Box 15)
      - H - O (Box 16)
      - P - Z (Box 17)
  - Card File B
    - A- Ma (Box 18)
    - Me - Z (Box 19)
  - Card File C
    - A - Cl (Box 19)
    - Co - Pl (Box 20)
    - Po - Z (Box 21)
- Series 14. Charter, 1932
  - Charter of William H. Hamilton Camp, Danielson, Conn., 1932 March 16 (Box Item 22)